<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog setup on Enrique Acosta Jaramillo</title>
    <link>https://enriqueacosta.github.io/blog/en/tags/blog-setup/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog setup on Enrique Acosta Jaramillo</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 21:12:04 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://enriqueacosta.github.io/blog/en/tags/blog-setup/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Creating This Blog Part 3: Tag Functionality and Listings, and Adding an About Page.</title>
      <link>https://enriqueacosta.github.io/blog/en/drafts/ode-to-brynes-euclid-reproduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 21:12:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://enriqueacosta.github.io/blog/en/drafts/ode-to-brynes-euclid-reproduction/</guid>
      <description>https://c82.net/blog/?id=79
https://c82.net/euclid/</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating This Blog Part 4: Adding a TikZ Gallery</title>
      <link>https://enriqueacosta.github.io/blog/en/posts/creating-this-blog-part-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 10:49:34 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://enriqueacosta.github.io/blog/en/posts/creating-this-blog-part-4/</guid>
      <description>TikZ is a programing language for creating images based on LaTeX. One writes TikZ &amp;ldquo;programing code&amp;rdquo; in a plain text file, and gets as output a pdf image file. The TikZ programming language was thought out to enable the code for a figure to be surprisingly human-readable. What I mean by this is that the reader can imagine the figure from the code because it looks like &amp;ldquo;drawing instructions for a human&amp;rdquo; instead of a bunch of obscure commands with lots hard to imagine numbers and coordinates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating This Blog Part 3: Tag Functionality and Listings, and Adding an About Page.</title>
      <link>https://enriqueacosta.github.io/blog/en/posts/creating-this-blog-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2022 21:12:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://enriqueacosta.github.io/blog/en/posts/creating-this-blog-part-3/</guid>
      <description>This is a follow-up to two previous posts ( here and here) describing how I set up this blog. Here I describe a couple of extra pieces of the setup including listing tags for each post, and adding the about page.
Listing the Tags for Each Post The Hyde theme, on which this Hugo site is based, does not list the post tags at the beginning of the page. I wanted to add this to the interface.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating This Blog Part 2: More Multilingual Support Using i18n</title>
      <link>https://enriqueacosta.github.io/blog/en/posts/creating-this-blog-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 21:12:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://enriqueacosta.github.io/blog/en/posts/creating-this-blog-part-2/</guid>
      <description>This is a follow-up to a previous post describing how I set up this blog. Here I describe setting up more elaborate multilingual support using i18n.
Multilingual Text &amp;ldquo;Snippets&amp;rdquo; Using i18n Hugo comes built in with i18n support. This is a very nice and simple way to specify fixed texts that should change according to the language. I call these &amp;ldquo;multilingual snippets&amp;rdquo;. To start using it all I had to do was create the files en.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating this Blog: Hugo, making the Hyde theme multilingual, and adding Latex support</title>
      <link>https://enriqueacosta.github.io/blog/en/posts/creating-this-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 22:49:34 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://enriqueacosta.github.io/blog/en/posts/creating-this-blog/</guid>
      <description>This blog does not live in a commercial platform for bloggers. It is what is technically called a &amp;ldquo;static site&amp;rdquo;, meaning it is just a collection of html files that are linked between each other and some other formatting files (css, for example). As such, it can be hosted anywhere and is not tied to any particular platform. Moreover, it was created with a fantastic open source tool caled Hugo. In this blog entry I explain how I set it up.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
